<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2019-12-08T12:52:37+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Derek Kedziora’s Blog</title><subtitle>Derek Kedziora's blog about the tech world, UX, writing and anything else that's worth being opinated about</subtitle><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><entry><title type="html">Antifragility Without Taleb</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/antifragility-over-talebism" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antifragility Without Taleb" /><published>2019-10-20T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2019-10-20T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/antifragility-over-talebism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/antifragility-over-talebism">&lt;p&gt;The concepts of antifragility and the black swan have become synonymous with Nassim Nicholas Taleb. This is unfortunate, as these ideas are not unique to him, and Taleb as a  social media drama queen is doing more to discrete his philosophy at this point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why it’s worth untangling the philosophy behind antifragility from partisan talking points, Twitter tantrums and poor examples in order to reveal a rich philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-substance-of-talebs-ideas&quot;&gt;The substance of Taleb’s ideas&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleb claims to intentionally write in meandering prose so that it’s impossible to summarize him. This, of course, is nonesense. His main ideas run something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;We like to think of the world in simple and predictable models. While this works much of the time, there are rare and seemingly unexpected fat tail events, known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_swan_theory&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;black swans&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Because our standard models don’t take black swans into account, hidden risk looms behind seemingly safe and predictable events.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Rather than maximizing gains during non-black-swan times, survival depends on the ability to weather black swans. Think of an asset portfolio that holds value during a recession. Contrast this with one optimized to grow during a bear market yet becomes worthless during a recession.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The most important ethical principle is &lt;em&gt;skin in the game&lt;/em&gt;, not separating risk from reward. Taxpayers bore the entire risk of banking in 2008, while only bankers reaped the profits.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Antifragility, the ability to become stronger in the midst of chaos and unpredictability, is even better than resiliency during a black swan event.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lindy_effect&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;Lindy effect&lt;/a&gt; informs what’s antifragile: the world is inherently conservative, things that have survived thousands of years are more likely to be antifragile than something new.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s nothing particularly controversial in the above points, which are laid out in &lt;em&gt;the Black Swan&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Antifragile&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These points run against the eternal growth at all costs ethos and pits Taleb against his fist wave of opponents. Take index fund investing. In normal times they provide a steady drip of returns from the stock market, but this is incredibly risky to use as a retirement plan. Had you retired in early 2007 to live off of index funds, you’d have lost most of your assets. This is Taleb’s point. We need systems that are designed to not blow up rather than temporarily maximize gains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleb takes the logic of antifragility beyond financial markets. Any institution that’s “too big to fail” creates risk and transfer it to society, because we know it will eventually fail on a long enough timeline. He also applies this to health: foods that have been eaten for thousands of years (better still, pre-agricultural foods) are better for us than official dietary recommendations. When you see people struggling with obesity and type II diabetes while dutifully eating what mainstream medicine tells them to, Taleb has a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleb liberally draws on the classics, which is to be expected from someone touting Lindy. This is where he’s a joy to read. Montaigne, the Stoics and early Christians were dealing with the same human condition as we are today. For many modern readers like myself, a turn to older literature and philosophy is eye opening. It’s largely thanks to Taleb that I became interested in ancient Western philosophy and have taken a more favorable view of religious philosophy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;taleb-the-persona&quot;&gt;Taleb the persona&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Had Taleb stuck to this general thesis, hashed it out with more examples and practical advice, I don’t think he’d be particularly controversial. But that’s not Taleb. Instead, he’s a pugnacious social media bully.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone who disagrees with Taleb is immediately branded an &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/incerto/the-intellectual-yet-idiot-13211e2d0577&quot; title=&quot;Medium&quot;&gt;intellectual yet idiot&lt;/a&gt;. It’s not that the piece about the IYI isn’t spot on in many cases. It is. I’ve met plenty of managers in the tech industry who are IYIs to a T. Nonetheless, describing every single person who disagrees with you as an idiot doesn’t build constructive dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleb doesn’t need dialogue or debate, since he’s &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; wrong in his own mind. Even when he’s obviously incorrect, he simply clamps down and screams about his opponents on Twitter. This is unfortunate. I’d love to see robust discussions and refinements of his ideas, the sort of respectful debates that are common on the so-called intellectual dark web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;deeper-scrutiny-of-talebs-examples&quot;&gt;Deeper scrutiny of Taleb’s examples&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The closer you start to scrutinize Taleb’s concrete positions, it’s apparent he’s a partisan hack and dilettante in many respects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of Taleb’s key ideas is &lt;em&gt;fuck you money&lt;/em&gt;. In theory, someone would have enough money to buy intellectual independence. He transfers this idea to a political doctrine that a business mogul makes an excellent ruler, since they have so much money as to no longer be interested in personal gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a lovely theory. Actual examples of this are few and far between. Instead, history is rife with examples of oligarchs turning to politics to serve their business interests. Even today, I don’t see Bill Gates working against the patent trolling that made him a billionaire or Warren Buffet campaigning against the anti-competitive moats. Billionaires might try to salvage their legacies, but even with what should be more than enough &lt;em&gt;fuck you money&lt;/em&gt;, they aren’t going to dismantle the system that made them rich.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleb also prides himself as being the ultimate bullshit detector. This makes his support for Tump all the more curious since most evidence points to Trump, his inner circle and appointees being grifters and seeking to maximize personal profit at public expense. Taleb fell for the reality TV persona of Donald Trump hook, line and sinker. This makes all the criticism of corruption under Obama a bad faith argument — the grift and personal enrichments under the Trumps are unprecedented.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much ink is devoted to attacking Saudi Arabia. It’s a fragile monarchy supported by oil that wages war and spreads its toxic ideology. No argument from me. My issue is that this is equally true of Russia, yet Taleb has nothing but fawning praise for Putin’s Russia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taleb claims to love localism and weak federal states. This is precisely what the EU is. A weak unifying structure that has made sub-national localism possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This type of hypocrisy and contradiction appears almost every time Taleb cites examples of his ideas. It’s unfortunate since it makes the whole concept of antifragility look like Ayn Rand 2.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-non-talebian-antifragility-reading-list&quot;&gt;The non-Talebian antifragility reading list&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Black Swan&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;Antifragile&lt;/em&gt; are fine reads if you’re willing to sift through the hubris to get at the good parts. Otherwise, there are better books that hit at the same concepts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HvoYwoCI7Mk&quot; title=&quot;YouTube&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Messy&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Tim Harford is the best place to start. It’s a fun read and introduces well-intended schemes that backfired. The real world is inherently messy and fighting against that yields unpredictable second-order consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not buying into the hype over technology is one of my favorite things about Taleb. Just throwing your hands in the air and screaming Lindy isn’t a great argument though. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Weapons_of_Math_Destruction&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Weapons of Math Destruction&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Cathy O’Neil lays bare some of the fallacies at the heart of techno-utopianism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lindy tends to cherry pick from the past, and is plagued by suvivorship bias. Evolution is a conservative process and classics have staying power, nonetheless it’s absurd to overlook the shortcomings of any supposed golden era in the past. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_World_Until_Yesterday&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;The World Until Yesterday&lt;/em&gt; &lt;/a&gt; by Jared Diamond get into this. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sapiens:_A_Brief_History_of_Humankind&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sapiens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; by Yuval Harari covers some of the same material but the techno-utopianism is a turn off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Christopher_McDougall&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;Christopher McDougall’s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;em&gt;Natural Born Heroes&lt;/em&gt; outlines most of the health claims Taleb talks about and is a great read to boot. For an even shorter introduction to antifragility and health, check out Scott Carney’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=lIm6H37-tbs&quot; title=&quot;YouTube&quot;&gt;TEDx talk&lt;/a&gt;. His book &lt;em&gt;What Doesn’t Kill US&lt;/em&gt; is worth the read if you are particularly interested in cold exposure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you want a modern introduction to the philosophers of yesteryear, you can’t go wrong with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sarah_Bakewell&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;Sarah Bakewell&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alain_de_Botton&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;Alain de Botton&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s just a start. There’s so much more to antifragility than Nassim Taleb.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><summary type="html">The concepts of antifragility and the black swan have become synonymous with Nassim Nicholas Taleb. This is unfortunate, as these ideas are not unique to him, and Taleb as a social media drama queen is doing more to discrete his philosophy at this point.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Just So Story of a Pronoun</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/pronouns" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Just So Story of a Pronoun" /><published>2019-08-18T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2019-08-18T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/pronouns</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/pronouns">&lt;p&gt;There’s something about language that makes linguistics a field rife with hubris. We know there’s something powerful about words, so we fight over them as a proxy for social movements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This energy is misplaced. No amount of fighting over pronouns is going to bring about the social change that pronounistas want. Instead of making political correctness, we should see it as the result of properly using emotional language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;emotional-manipulation-of-language&quot;&gt;Emotional manipulation of language&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Political correctness is cast as the primary manipulator of language. This belies the fact that the most powerful wordsmith in the US is, without a doubt, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Frank_Luntz&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;Frank Luntz&lt;/a&gt;. Thanks to Luntz, estate tax became “death tax” and people are terrified of the “government takeover of healthcare”. The GOP continues to successfully hoodwink people into voting against their interests by using emotionally manipulative language.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t underestimate the power of emotional manipulation. The core concept of the Affordable Care Act came from a conservative think tank and was first implemented by Mitt Romney. It was the conservative answer to a single payer system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cooperating with Obama to enact solidly conservative legislation was obviously unthinkable to the GOP. Thus, the name Obama, which right-wing media had already made synonymous with everything wrong in the world, was tacked on to healthcare reform. Obamacare. The result is that Kentuckians hate Obamacare but love it when it’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/2014/5/12/5709866/kentuckians-only-hate-obamacare-if-you-call-it-obamacare&quot; title=&quot;Vox&quot;&gt;called something else&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The success of Luntzian language doesn’t stop there. White supremacists quote Fox News talking points in their manifestos before they go on shooting sprees. Attaboy, Frank!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;grammatical-manipulation-of-language&quot;&gt;Grammatical manipulation of language&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Linguistic social justice warriors believe that changing the core characteristics of a language will bring about social change a la Luntzian black magic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s the old myth of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eskimo_words_for_snow&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;Eskimo words for snow&lt;/a&gt;: Inuit languages have a bunch of words for different types of snow because of its cultural significance. Taken further, Inuits are better at perceiving subtle variations in snow &lt;em&gt;because&lt;/em&gt; these words exist. The PC mythology hinges on the inverse being true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The logic runs thus:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Certain words are used almost exclusively in racist, sexist or other discriminatory contexts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Those words need to be eliminated from public discourse.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The elimination of these words means that racism and sexism have gone away.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m happy that the n-word can’t be dropped in casual conversation anymore, but that has hardly put a dent in institutional racism. Instead we have politicians and casual racists speaking in &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dog-whistle_politics&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;dog whistles&lt;/a&gt;. We’ve created a new absurdity of a genuine racist seriously thinking they aren’t racist since they don’t use the n-word. Is that real progress?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Going back to the Eskimos for a minute: the whole idea has long been disproven. English is just as descriptive as any Inuit language, we simply use adjectives and phrases instead of distinct nouns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, not having a specific word doesn’t mean a concept doesn’t exist. In English, there’s no direct equivalent of the Russian word сушняк, which specifically refers to the thirst experienced during a hangover. To posit that I never knew the agony of desperately wanting to rehydrate after a night of heavy drinking because English doesn’t have the word сушняк is idiotic. Yet this is precisely what the success of political correctness hinges on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;gendered-language&quot;&gt;Gendered language&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gender is hardcoded into European languages. Even less extravagant languages like English force you to classify &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt; as he, she or it. For transgender / non-binary / intersex activists and feminists this makes English and other European languages inherently discriminatory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The PC crowd is trying to spin a just so story that Sweden’s &lt;em&gt;hen&lt;/em&gt;, a newly minted gender-neutral pronoun, is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/actually-gender-neutral-pronouns-can-change-a-culture/&quot; title=&quot;Wired&quot;&gt;stamping out discrimination&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a two-pronged claim to unpack:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Gender neutral language causes rapid social change.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Social change is driven by linguistic change and not the other way around.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first claim is laughable. Kyrgyz and Uzbek don’t have gendered pronouns. It’s no secret that neither Kyrgyzstan nor Uzbekistan are feminist and non-binary paradises. If you go through the list of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gender_neutrality_in_genderless_languages&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;languages that are gender neutral&lt;/a&gt;, it’s hard to see any relationship between language and a country’s politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chinese presents an even more interesting case that Kyrgyz. Spoken Chinese doesn’t use gendered pronouns. That didn’t stop foot binding and widow suicide nor turn pre-modern China into an LGBT utopia. Incidentally, written Chinese added a feminine pronoun, 她, in the 20th Century under European influence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taiwan is a progressive society with relatively strong protection for transgender rights. Using the logic of the Swedish study, &lt;em&gt;adding&lt;/em&gt; gendered pronouns to a language reduced discrimination in Taiwan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact the billions of people have been using gender-neutral pronouns for millennia is uncomfortable to both sides of the PC debate. Conservatives can’t fear-monger over slipper slopes, while progressives can’t count on grammar rules to dictate social change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second claim, that the introduction of &lt;em&gt;hen&lt;/em&gt; in Swedish has &lt;em&gt;caused&lt;/em&gt; social change rather than social change driving the introduction of &lt;em&gt;hen&lt;/em&gt;, is equally tenuous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sweden of the 1960s illustrates this with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Du-reformen&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;Du-reformen&lt;/a&gt;. Social changes in Scandinavia caused the formal form of “you” to fall out of use. Nobody claims that dropping the formal form of “you” caused the changes. Hoping you can adopt the outward result of a change and somehow affect the change is literally the definition of cargo culting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spain and France are going through a similar shift at the moment, with tu / tous becoming the new default. The internet is behind this, not SJWs demanding change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rapidity of social change adds confusion to causality and was completely ignored by the Swedish researchers in question. It’s easy to forget that Obama was &lt;em&gt;against&lt;/em&gt; same-sex marriage as late as 2010. The same social forces were likely at play in Sweden during the same time period. I’d aver that the adoption of &lt;em&gt;hen&lt;/em&gt; is the result rather than the cause of social changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an aside, English has been using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Singular_they&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;singular they&lt;/a&gt; as a gender-neutral pronoun on and off since the 14th Century. Was Chaucer a non-binary feminist after all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;soft-strands-of-linguistic-determinism&quot;&gt;Soft strands of linguistic determinism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this is to say that language doesn’t influence us on some level. Serious linguists have discounted the strongest claims of the Sapir-Whorf hypothesis. There’s still some wiggle room left, though.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose you show a colored object to an English-speaker and ask that person a week later to recall what color the object was. Your test subject responds, “blue”. You press further, “Light or dark blue?”. An English-speaker very well may not remember the shade of blue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise would be impossible with a Russian speaker as there is no single word for blue. The Russian-speaker would have to choose either синний (dark blue) or голубой (light blue).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;English speakers are equally capable of distinguishing shades of blue; rather, they don’t add it to a narrative unless the shade is important. In this case, Russian and English are equally expressive, but they have different levels of minimum required information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soft linguistic determinism is such a narrow niche, that it seems odd to fight political battles with grammar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-power-and-impotence-of-words&quot;&gt;The power and impotence of words&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotionally manipulating words has a powerful effect on people. If you want to empower your social cause, grab a copy of Luntz’s &lt;em&gt;Words that Work&lt;/em&gt; and have at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Making low-level grammatical changes to a language in the hope that linguistic determinism will drive social change is tilting at windmills. For a look at how grammar shapes thinking, check out &lt;em&gt;Through the Language Glass&lt;/em&gt;. Don’t expect a blueprint for social engineering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many of today’s activists are fighting linguistic minutiae in the belief that winning these battles is how to master the emotional power of words. Pronouns are a lost cause, stories aren’t.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><summary type="html">There’s something about language that makes linguistics a field rife with hubris. We know there’s something powerful about words, so we fight over them as a proxy for social movements.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Adding Dark Mode to a Static Site</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/dark-mode" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Adding Dark Mode to a Static Site" /><published>2019-07-26T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2019-07-26T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/dark-mode</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/dark-mode">&lt;p&gt;The internet is finally viewing the ability to switch back and forth between a dark theme or night mode and a light mode as an important accessibility feature. It’s about time. Staring at an overly illuminated screen all day is hard on the eyes, and trying to reduce evening light exposure has worked wonders for my sleep quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have a static site—my blog is built with Jekyll, but this is same concept if you use Hugo or Gatsby, you can’t use the server to change your CSS from the backend to switch back and forth between light and dark modes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s three ways to change CSS on the front end so that whoever is reading a site will still in the color mode they selected:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Cookies&lt;/strong&gt;. A no go for me because the EU cookie thing is annoying.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;URL Parameters&lt;/strong&gt;. I got this to work, but URLs are clunky looking and this sometimes breaks navigation to different parts of the same page.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Local Storage.&lt;/strong&gt; The clear winner: unnoticeable to readers and works well with the new &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;prefers-color-scheme&lt;/code&gt; in CSS.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-concept&quot;&gt;The Concept&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be clear I wanted a switch that allows readers to select whichever color mode they want, and that mode needs to not revert to the default when someone navigates around the site. Furthermore, I didn’t want a flash of either black or white when moving between pages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This meant that I needed a button that triggered a script to change the page’s CSS and add local storage telling future page loads which color scheme to use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To make it even more complicated, I wanted the default to be day mode &lt;em&gt;unless&lt;/em&gt; someone’s system preferences were set to dark mode. Thus I’d need some frontend JavaScript to figure out what the color scheme of the initial page load and save the preference to local storage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-css&quot;&gt;The CSS&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On my first attempt, I used two CSS files and swapped them out based on the preferred color scheme. This caused flashes of white or black when moving between pages in Firefox and Chrome. This is a common shortcoming of a lot of sites with dark mode toggles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution is simple enough: use a single CSS file with variables. Here’s what my CSS looks like:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot; data-lang=&quot;css&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;data-theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&quot;light&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;],&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;py&quot;&gt;--light-text-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hsl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;35%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;py&quot;&gt;--main-background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hsl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;5%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;95%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;py&quot;&gt;--main-text-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hsl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;html&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;data-theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&quot;dark&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;]&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;py&quot;&gt;--light-text-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hsl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;60%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;py&quot;&gt;--main-background-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hsl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;10%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class=&quot;py&quot;&gt;--main-text-color&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;hsl&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;10%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;m&quot;&gt;80%&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, the light mode variables will be set and that’s how the site will load. To get dark mode to load, we have to use JavaScript to change HTML data attribute to “dark”. Going back to light mode is same in reverse, changing the HTML data attribute to “light”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, when you specify the colors for various elements in your CSS use the variables and not absolute values!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last bit of CSS is adding a way to detect whether a site visiter prefers dark mode:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-css&quot; data-lang=&quot;css&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;@media&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;prefers-color-scheme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;n&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;html&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class=&quot;nl&quot;&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;&quot;dark&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-button&quot;&gt;The button&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I put a simple button at the top of each page on my site:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-html&quot; data-lang=&quot;html&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;lt;button&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;id=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;theme-toggle&quot;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;na&quot;&gt;onclick=&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s&quot;&gt;&quot;modeSwitcher()&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nt&quot;&gt;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;/button&amp;gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-javascript&quot;&gt;The JavaScript&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the very top of the page, I inserted a tiny script to check if dark mode has already been entered into local storage. If you run this at the end of the page, you’ll get a white flash when navigating between posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;theme&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;localStorage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;theme&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;===&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;documentElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setAttribute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;data-theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of each page I inserted this script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-javascript&quot; data-lang=&quot;javascript&quot;&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;const&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;userPrefers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getComputedStyle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;documentElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getPropertyValue&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;content&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;	

&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;theme&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;===&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;theme-toggle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;innerHTML&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Light Mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;theme&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;===&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;light&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;theme-toggle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;innerHTML&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Dark Mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt;  &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;userPrefers&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;===&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;documentElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setAttribute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;data-theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;localStorage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;theme-toggle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;innerHTML&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Light Mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;documentElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setAttribute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;data-theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;light&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;localStorage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;light&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;theme-toggle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;innerHTML&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Dark Mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;function&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;modeSwitcher&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;()&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;kd&quot;&gt;let&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;currentMode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;documentElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getAttribute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;data-theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;if&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;currentMode&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;===&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;)&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;documentElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setAttribute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;data-theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;light&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;localStorage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;light&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;theme-toggle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;innerHTML&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Dark Mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;k&quot;&gt;else&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;documentElement&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setAttribute&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;data-theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;window&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;localStorage&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;setItem&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;theme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;,&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s1&quot;&gt;dark&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;'&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;);&lt;/span&gt;
		&lt;span class=&quot;nb&quot;&gt;document&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;getElementById&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;theme-toggle&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;).&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;nx&quot;&gt;innerHTML&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;o&quot;&gt;=&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;s2&quot;&gt;Light Mode&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;dl&quot;&gt;&quot;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;;&lt;/span&gt;
	&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class=&quot;p&quot;&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This script checks if a visitor prefers dark mode, and if so applies dark mode and notes it in local storage. If someone clicks the button, the mode gets changed and local storage updated accordingly. Additionally, the text of the button is updated to match the current color mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-result&quot;&gt;The result&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like magic, you now have a dark mode toggle that works on a static site. You can have fun with this and add toggles for other things like sans-serif or serif fonts.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><category term="programming" /><summary type="html">The internet is finally viewing the ability to switch back and forth between a dark theme or night mode and a light mode as an important accessibility feature. It’s about time. Staring at an overly illuminated screen all day is hard on the eyes, and trying to reduce evening light exposure has worked wonders for my sleep quality.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Keeping Politics Out of Identity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/politics-identity" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Keeping Politics Out of Identity" /><published>2019-07-09T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2019-07-09T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/politics-identity</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/politics-identity">&lt;p&gt;And so the Fourth of July came and went.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To the Trumpian Right, this was a moment of unequivocal glory — their identity indivisibly tied to military hardware rumbling through the capital. Seemingly, the only alternative is decrying caged people drinking from toilets on the Southern Border as un-American.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet either approach is dangerous. If there’s anything to learn from European history, it’s that wrapping identity in ideology, flags and partisan politics doesn’t end well. We’re quickly losing apolitical space in the US, which is something that should alarm us more than any individual politician.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;identity&quot;&gt;Identity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To me, and I’d aver to most people around the world, national identity is a combination of the place I was born, the way I grew up speaking, the food I eat and a tapestry of local customs. None of these are political. Celebrating my country of birth doesn’t require a foray into the political realm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shouldn’t like either Trumpism or the Left hijack identity. Being American doesn’t make me an Evangelical Christian praying for war with Iran anymore than it makes me support the du jour social justice cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This entire conversation shows the complete and utter victory of Trumpism as a paradigm. Even the most vigorous opponents of the President accept the same fundamentals. One’s identity as an American hinges on their either being a Southern Border wall or an open border. Of course, I have my opinion on the efficacy of wall as political solution, but that opinion has no bearing on my Americanness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I say that Trumpism has won, because even non-Trump supporters accept, on some level, that the United States is equivalent to the government. Thus, it follows that discontent with the government is tantamount to rejection of one’s identity as an American.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is ahistorical. Europeans have been forging a New-World identity for half a millennium, indigenous peoples far longer. The modern American Republic represents only half of the time that English-speakers have been living in North America. The East Coast cities are older than many of the “ye olde towne” tourists traps in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a slight of the hand to identify America with a government that’s been a blip on the radar in the history of the land. That’s why I’m frustrated that holidays that were once apolitical have been coopted into the regime’s narrative.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;exceptionalism-and-superlatives&quot;&gt;Exceptionalism and superlatives&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I see this tendency on the left, albeit in a different form. America still must be spoken of in the superlative. The US is the worst country ever because the government doesn’t recognize the pronouns someone’s transgender dog prefers. Meh.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any other land and the various people living on it, the US has had its ups and downs. Among the ups, eradicating smallpox and polio seem to get overlooked while more dubious things like ‘democracy’ are heralded—as if something that peoples have been experimenting with for thousands of years was invented in America. The downs are obvious. What’s lost in the fray is that the US is just like any other country, simply more noticeable because of its scale.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-modern-politique&quot;&gt;A modern politique&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is obviously not the first time in history that opposing political factions have seen their squabble as taking on existential significance. And no, this is also not the first time that a regime has tried to insert itself into every facet of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Resistance isn’t isn’t screaming down Trump supporters in the streets, it’s doing something apolitical and approaching politics rationally. There’s a discussion to be had about the amount of immigration that would lead to economic growth without driving down wages. Such is impossible in our currently climate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My position is modern rendering of the &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Politique&quot; title=&quot;wikipedia.org&quot;&gt;politiques&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;, who sought to avoid the religious wars of 15th century France with political compromise. As long as political questions are framed in terms of good and evil as well as tied to national identity, there’s no hope for compromise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://sarahbakewell.com/&quot; title=&quot;sarahbakewell.com&quot;&gt;Sarah Bakewell&lt;/a&gt; describes the &lt;em&gt;politiques&lt;/em&gt; thus in her book on Montaigne, &lt;em&gt;How to Live&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There was indeed much of Stoic philosophy in the &lt;em&gt;politiques&lt;/em&gt;. They did not urge revolution or regicide, but recommended acceptance of life as it is, on the Stoic principle of &lt;em&gt;amor fati&lt;/em&gt;, or love of fate. They also promoted the Stoic sense of continuity: the belief that the world would probably continue to cycle through episodes of decay and rejuvenation, rather than accelerating into a one-directional rush towards the End. While the religious parties imagined the armies of Armageddon assembling in the sky, &lt;em&gt;politiques&lt;/em&gt; suspected that sooner or later everything would calm down and people would come back to their senses. In millenarian times, they were the only people systematically to shift their perspective and think ahead to a time when the “troubles” would have become history—and to plan exactly how to build this future world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t escapism. Instead, this taking the long view of politics. Stepping away from the brink of alarmism on a personal level is the first step in healing a society that’s in a stupor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-birthright-to-an-identity&quot;&gt;A birthright to an identity&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The identity that I was born with and was shaped throughout my formative years can’t be politicized. My native language, habits, where I grew up — none of these can be changed by whom I vote for. Trying to rob someone of their birthright over day-to-day political views is the beginning of political violence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence, I’ll hold firm in not speaking of the US as neither a country on a hill or the scourge of the earth. Likewise, I’ll continue to see my American identity as unrelated to any government, political ideology or person.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><summary type="html">And so the Fourth of July came and went.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My Midsummer Reading List</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/mid-2019-reading" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My Midsummer Reading List" /><published>2019-06-21T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2019-06-21T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/mid-2019-reading</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/mid-2019-reading">&lt;p&gt;The two paper books I just finished were both impulse buys from the bookstore. Apparently you don’t need an optimized algorithm to find a good read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;messy-by-tim-harford&quot;&gt;Messy by Tim Harford&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the cleanest takedown of compulsive orderliness I’ve ever read. A profusion of vignettes illustrates the folly of imposing a neat order on the natural world — from German experiments in forestry to over-automation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/antifragility-over-talebism&quot; title=&quot;Antifragility Yes, Talab Not So Much&quot;&gt;Taleb tried to accomplish in &lt;em&gt;Antifragile&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; — yet got lost in braggadocio, Harford does effortlessly. The vision of imposing a neat order on the natural world is a false messiah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed the long sections about music. Brian Eno artificially created chaos in the recording studio;  inauspicious conditions led to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=T_IW1wLZhzE&quot; title=&quot;The Köln Concert&quot;&gt;Keith Jarret’s greatest concert&lt;/a&gt;. I have a tendency to look for the &lt;em&gt;best&lt;/em&gt; workflow, the &lt;em&gt;most productive&lt;/em&gt; software and optimize everything. This served as a powerful reminder to back away from perfection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps too obvious to be profound, I keep coming back to the ideas in &lt;em&gt;Messy&lt;/em&gt;. Add spontaneity and improvisation to your life. You don’t need perfect tools. Enjoy the chaos and “imperfections” of nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s refreshing to read an author’s blog that hashes out original ideas rather than being a mere marketing pitch. &lt;a href=&quot;http://timharford.com/2019/05/the-art-of-time-well-spent/&quot; title=&quot;The Art of Time Well Spent&quot;&gt;The Art of Time Well Spent&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://timharford.com/2019/06/why-brilliant-people-lose-their-touch/&quot; title=&quot;Why Brilliant People Lose their Touch&quot;&gt;Why Brilliant People Lose their Touch&lt;/a&gt; are  worth a read.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;21-lessons-for-the-21st-century&quot;&gt;21 Lessons for the 21st Century&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s be honest, Harari is just cashing in on the success of &lt;em&gt;Sapiens&lt;/em&gt; with this one. Nonetheless, the book served its purpose of keeping me occupied for a few flights.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harari is oddly optimistic about technology, which seems odd given his personal history as a gay Israeli. To view technology as liberating is highly selective. It was modern technology that allowed the Germans to kill Harari’s relatives. A techno-dystopia is perhaps more plausible than a &lt;em&gt;Jetsons&lt;/em&gt; future. Harari avoids this uncomfortable discussion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to live in Tel Aviv and forget that most of humanity lives in a completely different reality. Israel is surrounded by countries that imprison, even execute homosexuals. Seeing a future dominated by liberal values instead of religious fundamentalism is a Fukuyamiam assumption without much factual basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most powerful chapter in the book focused on human reason and arguments. There is no empirical evidence to suggest that most people use logic, facts and research to understand issues and make informed decisions. There’s little hope of presenting evidence to encourage people to change their minds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This renders most political discourse moot. Our primate brains work on emotion and the logic of the savannas whence we evolved. We pretend otherwise at our own peril.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last chapter was an exploration of Hariri’s meditation practice. I always enjoy reading out other meditators approach the discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;infantile-design&quot;&gt;Infantile design&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://reallifemag.com/the-babysitters-club/&quot; title=&quot;The Babysitters Club&quot;&gt;The Babysitters Club&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://thebaffler.com/latest/the-corporate-logo-singularity-hawley&quot; title=&quot;The Corporate Logo Singularity&quot;&gt;the Corporate Logo Singularity&lt;/a&gt; hit at something that I haven’t been able to put my finger on. Corporate design and expert UX types are talking to us as if we were children. I see a future of increasingly useless devices with a bunch of peppy apps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I already have a nice stack of books to get me through the rest of the summer!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><summary type="html">The two paper books I just finished were both impulse buys from the bookstore. Apparently you don’t need an optimized algorithm to find a good read.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Life around the Universe</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/other-civilizations" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Life around the Universe" /><published>2019-05-11T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2019-05-11T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/other-civilizations</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/other-civilizations">&lt;p&gt;A recent visit to the Lowell Observatory in Flagstaff got me thinking about life around the solar system, and there are surprisingly many places that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/15716-alien-life-search-solar-system.html&quot; title=&quot;space.com&quot;&gt;could support life&lt;/a&gt;. If we eventually find life in a multiple places, that makes it far more probable that biological life is widespread across the universe. This &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; banish our remaining thoughts of anthropocentrism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/static/posts/2019-05-11/boga-net.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Soviet cosmonaut showing there is not God&quot; title=&quot;Бога нет!&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;A stopped clock…&lt;/figcaption&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The narrow meaning of life as something created by the God of Abraham doesn’t stand up when we start seeing the emergence of life as a natural feature of our universe. Instead of closing the door on finding meaning, this raises a host of new questions about consciousness and what defines life and cultrure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;inevitability&quot;&gt;Inevitability&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the search for life around the solar system only turns up clumps of bacteria, it’d be harder to shake our deep-seated anthropocentrism. Nonetheless, that’d still be the wrong conclusion to draw. &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abiogenesis&quot; title=&quot;wikipedia.org&quot;&gt;Abiogenesis&lt;/a&gt;, going from molecules to life is still opaque. Going from cells to consciousness is even more shrouded in mystery. If the right physical conditions are met, does that mean the emergence of life is inevitable, probable or something bordering on miraculous? The scale of time involved makes this &lt;em&gt;de facto&lt;/em&gt; untestable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The curious cases of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vice.com/en_us/article/vb9bpm/this-bird-went-extinct-and-then-evolved-into-existence-again&quot; title=&quot;vice.com&quot;&gt;iterative evolution&lt;/a&gt;, a species going extinct only for it to evolve back into existence, suggests that given specific parameters, evolution has a probabilistic outcome. There are enough of cases of extinct species not re-evolving to suggest that outcome of evolution is far from inevitable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s a tendency to look back at history as inevitable, yet there’s no real evidence to suggest that determinism quite so hard. I don’t see the transition of &lt;em&gt;homo sapiens&lt;/em&gt; from minor bands of hunter-gathers to agrarian and industrial societies as inevitable. Whether the jump to agriculture was a random event or shaped by climatic and geographic forces, it’s entirely reasonable to envision humans — in the broad sense of the term — staying hunter-gathers on some timeline. Large swathes of humanity remained so until relatively recently, although &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Uncontacted_peoples&quot; title=&quot;wikipedia.org&quot;&gt;uncontacted peoples&lt;/a&gt; are dwindling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose we find the universe is full of planets with human-like hunter-gathers living lives that they find meaningful without much of anything we’d call civilization? Would we judge them as somehow inferior to us? We like to think that the brutishness of Europe circa 1492 has passed. The current treatment of indigenous peoples says otherwise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The question can be adapted to a world without human-like life. Would we consider whales to be an advanced civilization? As far as we know, whales use language to communicate, transmit knowledge and form dialect groups. The problem with consciousness is that we have no way to examine a whale’s first-person experience of the world. As of now we’re left only with indirect ways to guess at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cetacean_intelligence&quot; title=&quot;wikipedia.org&quot;&gt;cetacean intelligence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Having a meaningful exchange with an alien culture is far fetched. There are many ‘alien’ cultures on this very earth that those of us in the industrialized West have no contact with. Papua New Guinea with its patchwork of languages and ethnicities is barely a blip on the radar, despite the fact that it offers a genuinely different perspective on the fundamental questions about the meaning of culture and life. I hope I’m wrong, but I find it even more unlikely that we’ll try to learn from animals with meta-cognitive awareness in my lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;further-thought-experiments&quot;&gt;Further thought experiments&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides looking out there for ‘alien’ civilizations, it’s entirely possible that an advanced, industrial civilization previously existed on earth. If such a society existed, we’d have &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2018/04/are-we-earths-only-civilization/557180/&quot; title=&quot;theatlantic.com&quot;&gt;little trace of it today&lt;/a&gt;. The river of time would wipe away all of their plastic, metal and anything else they’d built.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some sense, this is comforting. Humans can’t permanently deface the earth. Our planet could go through several cycles of complete biological extinction followed by a new course of evolution — all before the sun expands and then dies itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This comes with a caveat. Venus was once little different than the earth in terms of climate. Life could have existed there before being wiped out by catastrophic climate change. Mars also used to have a similar climate to earth. The possibility of ‘alien’ life extends out temporarily as well as spatially. Imagining a venetian or martian civilization obliterated as their climate lost the ability to sustain life hits a bit too close to home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some would argue that these thought experiments are a waste of time — we’d be better off focusing on problems more in the here and now. This is a cop out. Opening our minds to what is beyond the here and now is one of the most surefire ways to generate the empathy needed to solve the the crises of our generation. Whether it be learning from remote cultures on earth, realizing that the animals we see everyday have their own non-anthropomorphic cultures or the possibility of life scattered throughout the universe — acknowledging our own humility before the majesty of the universe is a cathartic path that each of us should experience.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><summary type="html">A recent visit to the Lowell Observatory in Flagstaff got me thinking about life around the solar system, and there are surprisingly many places that could support life. If we eventually find life in a multiple places, that makes it far more probable that biological life is widespread across the universe. This should banish our remaining thoughts of anthropocentrism.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Self-Driving Cars Are Corporate FOMO</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/glomar-cars" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Self-Driving Cars Are Corporate FOMO" /><published>2019-04-14T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2019-04-14T00:00:00+03:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/glomar-cars</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/glomar-cars">&lt;p&gt;Ford is already &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2019-04-09/ford-ceo-tamps-down-expectations-for-first-autonomous-vehicles&quot; title=&quot;Bloomberg&quot;&gt;lowering expectations for self-driving cars&lt;/a&gt;. This should give investors and techies pause and raise deeper epistemological questions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Tempering expectations isn’t isolated to Ford. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnet.com/news/alphabet-google-waymo-ceo-john-krafcik-autonomous-cars-wont-ever-be-able-to-drive-in-all-conditions/&quot; title=&quot;cnet&quot;&gt;Waymo has done the same&lt;/a&gt;. Tesla hits stationary objects. We’re not there yet. According to Waymo, we’re decades out.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lyft and Uber’s valuations only make sense if autonomous vehicles are just around the corner. As it stands, they both are losing billions a year.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is in stark contrast to the average person believing fully automated cars are a foregone conclusion. Capitalism is supposed to prevent these vast inefficiencies and weed out obvious frauds — I can see no description more apt for Uber and Lyft’s valuations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;corporate-fomo&quot;&gt;Corporate FOMO&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Managerial types have been using the fear of missing out (FOMO) to get consumers to spend more money for decades. You buy something because you’re afraid of either falling behind socially (wearing last season’s fashion — oh the humanity!) or because of an artificial scarcity (‘limited edition’).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Somehow the managerial types didn’t realize that marketing tricks work on them too. Thus we see a feedback loop with hucksters like Elon Musk continually upping the ante. After all, you don’t get billions of dollars in other people’s money to build a slight improvement over cruise control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tweet proclaims the inevitability of fully autonomous cars: meaning you hop in, take a nap and wake up across town. Tech journalist quote the tweet, which was originally marketing hype, to write a myriad of stories about self-driving cars being just around the corner. The second wave of journalism quotes the first stories as irrefutable evidence. Now there’s VC money to be had. Thus you need to invoke the lore of autonomous vehicles to unlock funding. Then the tech journalist quote the next wave of VC funded ‘founders’ whose entire livelihood depends on keeping the autonomous driving saga alive. Meanwhile the actual ‘autonomous cars’ that we’ll get are nothing like the hop in and take a nap thing we were expecting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If it were just the flunkies and tech wannabes that bought into the hype, that’d be one thing. Instead, full on FOMO has engulfed the automotive industry. Serious investors talk about throwing money in companies that &lt;em&gt;could&lt;/em&gt; become only if fully self-driving cars are worked out. This goes for everything from taxis to delivery. The whole economy is going to be disrupted!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I casually mention my lack of enthusiasm for self-driving cars among people in the tech bubble, I get blank stares and nervous laughs. I might as well be a flat-earther.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;howard-hughes-and-deep-sea-mining&quot;&gt;Howard Hughes and deep-sea mining&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Glomar_Explorer&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia&quot;&gt;Howard Hughes and the Glomar Explorer&lt;/a&gt; is more than a fascinating tale of Cold War spycraft. The CIA needed to build a massive ship without revealing that the true purpose of the operation was to raise a sunken Soviet submarine. An eccentric magnate known for moonshots came in handy. Howard Hughes would ostensibly build the &lt;em&gt;Glomar&lt;/em&gt; for deep-sea mining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t a case of the technology not panning out. It was &lt;em&gt;never&lt;/em&gt; real. That didn’t stop the media and other companies from catching wind of the operation and jumping on the bandwagon. Corporate FOMO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As far as I know, there was no public discussions of epistemology among journalists that hyped up deep-sea mining. I somehow doubt that the executives who authorized millions of dollars in FOMO inspired R&amp;amp;D spending had a retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike bubbles such as Bitcoin, the early dot-com era or tulips, this was always fake. To quote from a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/resources/idt-sh/deep_sea_mining&quot; title=&quot;BBC&quot;&gt;BBC story&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;To convince them that Howard Hughes was genuinely interested in nodules, executives were despatched to conferences on ocean mining where they described in detail their plans to harvest the rocks.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;“We made ocean mining seem a lot more credible,” Sharp says. “We really misled a lot of people and it’s surprising that the story held together for so long.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;The cover was so good that it prompted US universities to move to start courses in deep sea mining and it also whipped up the share prices of the companies involved. “People thought, ‘if Howard Hughes is into it, we need to be too’,” says Sharp.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s easy to laugh this off, but there’s something serious about human nature here. Real experts failed to sniff out bullshit. We should be humble about our own abilities to filter signal and noise. In fact we should learn to be far more skeptical of just about everything.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;no-harm-no-foul-right&quot;&gt;No harm, no foul. Right?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say that fully autonomous vehicles are a complete pipe dream for at least the next decade or two. The money spent didn’t go into a blackhole, jobs were created and the technology can be spun off into usable pursuits. If VCs want to subsidize my taxi fair, what’s the harm? Not so fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-driving cars are trying to solve a real transportation problem. Instead of a civic discourse about infrastructure, improved public transportation and urban planning that would eliminate the need for cars altogether, billionaires are gambling on getting even richer. The opportunity cost has been enormous, and many people have stopped working on the problem because of the belief that self-driving cars in the next couple of years is an inevitability.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at all of the VC money, resources, talent and energy being thrown at the blockchain and even less useful ‘innovations’ is even more depressing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;the-role-of-healthy-skepticism&quot;&gt;The role of healthy skepticism&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even the best and the brightest are subject to the fallacies and weaknesses of the human brain. A brilliant scientist still can fall for group think and FOMO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both corporate and government led innovation are vital for society. Nonetheless, that’s not an excuse for irrational exuberance. Those of us in tech need to respect skepticism instead of deriding it as a sign of Luddism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As people taking part of the public discourse, we need to be more demanding of journalists. Are they quoting a marketer as if they were a scientist? Is an accepted opinion coming from a hype feedback loop or actual science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the best heuristics for filtering out hubris in tech is to ask whether some hyped technology is trying to solve a political problem. An even better heuristic to sniff out bullshit is to ignore whatever tech journalists are calling disruptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s plenty of real innovation going on out there, but it’s behind the scenes. I’m loath to praise Amazon, but their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.economist.com/business/2019/04/13/amazons-empire-rests-on-its-low-key-approach-to-ai&quot; title=&quot;The Economist&quot;&gt;approach to machine learning&lt;/a&gt; has far more to offer than whatever Tech Crunch is talking about this week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Far more important than vanity and convenience tech is the research is vastly improving cancer treatment, leaving fewer people hungry and vaccinating more diseases out of existence.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><category term="tech" /><summary type="html">Ford is already lowering expectations for self-driving cars. This should give investors and techies pause and raise deeper epistemological questions.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why B2B Marketers Shouldn’t Growth Hack</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/b2b-marketing" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why B2B Marketers Shouldn't Growth Hack" /><published>2019-03-20T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-03-20T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/b2b-marketing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/b2b-marketing">&lt;p&gt;I took a year-long break from the product world to take over marketing for a small IT outsourcing company. I’d done content marketing before and written UX and marketing copy for a SaaS product with millions of users. What could be so hard about using this experience to dive into B2C marketing?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a year, sales were up and the number of employees grew by a third. We’d moved from working with only North American clients to Europe and the Middle East. That should be unequivocal success. I ended up leaving in frustration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest mistake small companies make with DIY marketing is reading a bunch of marketing hacks. I set up metrics from the the growth hacking genre such as subscribers, social media engagement and backlinks. I soon learned that it was possible to fail in all of these categories but still sell. In hindsight, the problem is obvious: I was using B2C tactics and metrics on a long-cycle B2B service. Nonetheless, I managed to be a successful marketer if we measure success as more clients. I didn’t hit any of my OKRs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;dont-let-hype-tell-you-how-to-market&quot;&gt;Don’t let hype tell you how to market&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hype driven managers are your number one obstacle as a B2B marketer. These are the types that spend their days reading inspiration blog posts, calling pointless meetings and trying to micromanage their marketers. Think Michael Scott meet’s Taleb’s intellectual yet idiot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hype driven managers are hopelessly impractical. Why use a Google Sheet when you could build a Rube Goldberg data monster out of a dozen SaaS apps? A completely unrelated product with a different market went viral, how come our posts don’t have that many likes on Facebook? Let’s change strategy every few weeks. My experience shows that a lot of managers at venture funded companies are &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/dataism&quot; title=&quot;derekkedziora.com&quot;&gt;hype driven data-ists&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This stems from the mass psychosis known as venture capital. Sustainable growth and profit are passé. Going viral, regardless of whether it brings you any benefit, and loosing money are the marks of a successful business in 2019. The media fawns over Uber and Lyft as they lose billions each year, while Apple is castigated for turning a profit. This approach has filtered down to nearly every manager in the tech industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after successfully converting a lead, I’m challenged for not building a scalable system. This is patently absurd. Small companies don’t need scalability or viral social media posts. They need clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Don’t turn to HubSpot for your B2B marketing. They’ll happily sell you the functionality of a spreadsheet for hundreds of dollars a month plus a tall tale of scalability. Neil Patel will have you spending money to get to the top of Google, but that’s no guarantee you’ll get paying clients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Growth marketing hacks tend to work for products with a short conversion cycle. This is what marketing marketers are selling you. The most important thing I learned as a B2B marketer was to ignore all of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;know-your-sales-cycle&quot;&gt;Know your sales cycle&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It pays to think of the non-digital equivalent of your product. Are you McDonald’s — cheap, consistent, reliable and profitable because of quick turnover? A fast food joint gets people in the door with cheap, quick food. Are you positioned in a place where people looking for affordable and fast solutions?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s say you’re more of a BMW: expensive but powerful, secure and high-quality. Does a BMW dealership go to the closest bus stop and offer free test drives in order to increase engagement? There’s not a lot of overlap between potential BMW customers and people waiting for a bus, yet hype driven managers do the digital equivalent of this each time they check on the social media likes of their latest blog post. There’s nothing wrong with McDonald’s, but their marketing approach isn’t going to work to sell BMWs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve figured out whether you’re selling Big Macs or BMWs, you can make more informed decisions about whether to focus your energy on email subscriptions, blogging, business platforms like Clutch, cold emails or LinkedIn. Small companies don’t have the resources to do it all.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;blogging-and-content-for-long-cycle-b2b-sales&quot;&gt;Blogging and content for long-cycle B2B sales&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A good blog that churns out several long posts a weeks is expensive. Writers aren’t cheap and anything beyond a cookie-cutter Wordpress theme requires serious development time. Throw in some designer hours and you’ve got a real investment. My experience is that most companies with blogs aren’t actually doing the math to see whether it’s worth it. Too many blogs exist because of FOMO.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You’ll never compete with massive companies that have entire blog teams replete with writers, designers and SEO specialists. These teams pump out two to three posts a week and have huge semi-kosher linking schemes. Compete where you can win, which is usually domain expertise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Write long, informative posts about your company’s expertise 1–3 times a quarter.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Well written whitepapers and customer stories are important for long sales cycles.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Clear landing page copy makes the first impression that you need.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atrium.co/blog/seo-seed-stage-startups/&quot; title=&quot;atrium.com&quot;&gt;SEO Playbook&lt;/a&gt; became my bible for writing blog posts. &lt;a href=&quot;https://dockyard.com&quot; title=&quot;dockyard.com&quot;&gt;Dockyard&lt;/a&gt; nails landing page copy and customer stories. Shamelessly steal their style: make it clear what you do and how it benefits other companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;outreach-emails&quot;&gt;Outreach emails&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cold emails and LinkedIn messages worked far better than I expected. There’s true spam, where you just randomly send out a long email to someone that has a low probability needing your services. Don’t do that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It takes time, but market research pays off. If you specialize in Python and TensorFlow, you’ll get a much higher ROI on your marketing by emailing companies looking for Python developers rather than randomly spamming every Bay Area tech company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Always write about what you can do for your potential clients. Nobody cares about you. And nobody wants to click your HubSpot calendar link. Act like a human and ask when would be a good time for a quick call.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Real social proof is powerful. Mentioning that you work with other companies in the same city or have solved similar problems in a different industry means more than including your NPS in a marketing email.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;racing-to-the-bottom&quot;&gt;Racing to the bottom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sites like Clutch can get you a lot of prospects. It’d be a mistake to avoid them entirely, but companies need to keep an eye on the ROI of business listings. The average prospect contacts a dozen companies, eats up a lot of your time getting a proposal, going back and forth, squeezing what free consulting out of you and then going with the cheapest offer. Unless you’re based in South Asia, you’re not going to win at this game.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;social-media-silos&quot;&gt;Social media silos&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I found Twitter and Facebook to be big time wasters. Posts rarely broke out of the silo of our followers, which were employees and their relatives. If your potential customer is 99% of the planet, that’s a start. It’s useless for B2B marketing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reposting blog posts to Medium, although be sure to import rather than copying and pasting, was the best way to reach outside of our silos. Also, being published in a prestigious publication carries a lot more street cred than linking to a company blog.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;doing-what-works&quot;&gt;Doing what works&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My bottom line is doing whatever brings in clients. This is the single metric that matters. A simple combination of google analytics, a few blog posts, some emails and a spreadsheet is all you need to get and record meaningful data without becoming &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/fake-data&quot; title=&quot;derekkedziora.com&quot;&gt;fake data driven&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Management and marketing need to agree on a few assumptions for marketing to work at a small B2B business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Are you selling Big Macs or BMWs?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What metrics match your sales cycle?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;How do you plan to reach your potential clients and what resources do you need in order to do so?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Stick with it. Marketing campaigns take months to mature.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Successful B2B marketing is possible, even for small businesses with a limited budget. The key is ignoring hype driven management, not trying to port growth marketing hacks from the VC world and some old fashioned hard work.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><category term="marketing" /><summary type="html">I took a year-long break from the product world to take over marketing for a small IT outsourcing company. I’d done content marketing before and written UX and marketing copy for a SaaS product with millions of users. What could be so hard about using this experience to dive into B2C marketing?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What I’m Reading: Early 2019</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/reading-early-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What I'm Reading: Early 2019" /><published>2019-03-03T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-03-03T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/reading-early-2019</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/reading-early-2019">&lt;p&gt;The winter of 2018–2019 has been hectic with a new job and over a month on the road. Nonetheless, I’ve snuck in some reading time and mulled over plenty of ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;books&quot;&gt;Books&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I blew through &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-democracies-die&quot; title=&quot;How Democracies Die&quot;&gt;How Democracies Die&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; in a few days. It’s not merely another book cashing in on the anti-Trump bandwagon. The lessons for democracy are much more universal. I highly recommend it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m stuck about a third of the way through &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Independent_People&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia.org&quot;&gt;Independent People&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Yes, it’s great, but it’s also heavy reading. With fiction, I either love it or can’t finish it. Maybe the the themes are too obvious, the personalities too caricatured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://basecamp.com/books/getting-real&quot; title=&quot;basecamp.com&quot;&gt;Getting Real&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; was a work read. It’s worth a skim. The premise is to focus on real metrics and build simple, opinionated products. I’ve seen the opposite in action: managers that care more about vanity metrics as the ship is sinking. It ain’t pretty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reflecting-on-data&quot;&gt;Reflecting on Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://apenwarr.ca/log/20190201&quot; title=&quot;apenwarr.ca&quot;&gt;Forget Privacy: You’re Terrible at Targeting Anyway&lt;/a&gt; is a must read for the &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/dataism&quot; title=&quot;The Absurdity of Data-ism&quot;&gt;data skeptics&lt;/a&gt; out there. The takeaway is that we’re not really getting anything cool in return for letting companies analyze our data. Most of what we generate sits unanalyzed in forgotten databases. Not enough businesses are asking whether we can get profitable ads and recommendations without personalized data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a hard argument to present and win when you’re talking to managerial types. Three eloquent points in &lt;a href=&quot;https://seths.blog/2019/02/the-am-pm-problem-the-curse-of-too-much-data/&quot; title=&quot;Seth Godin&quot;&gt;Data is Expensive&lt;/a&gt; say what took me an &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/data-driven-marketing-in-a-web-of-fake-data-e13995e448c8&quot;&gt;entire blog post&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;First, don’t collect data unless it has a non-zero chance of changing your actions.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Second, before you seek to collect data, consider the costs of processing that data.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Third, acknowledge that data collected isn’t always accurate, and consider the costs of acting on data that’s incorrect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that collecting and processing data becomes an ethical conundrum akin to working in gambling or arms dealing. The question is more serious than an afternoon lost to YouTube. China is already a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2019/3/1/18246297/china-transportation-people-banned-poor-social-credit-planes-trains-2018&quot; title=&quot;The Verge&quot;&gt;data dystopia&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;animal-consciousness&quot;&gt;Animal Consciousness&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more I meditate, the less I understand consciousness. The hard sciences aren’t any closer. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/magazine/archive/2019/03/what-the-crow-knows/580726/&quot; title=&quot;The Atlantic&quot;&gt;A Journey Into the Animal Mind&lt;/a&gt; is a slow, philosophical read. From the article:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Even in a secular age, consciousness retains a mystical sheen. It is alternatively described as the last frontier of science, and as a kind of immaterial magic beyond science’s reckoning. David Chalmers, one of the world’s most respected philosophers on the subject, once told me that consciousness could be a fundamental feature of the universe, like space-time or energy. He said it might be tied to the diaphanous, indeterminate workings of the quantum world, or something nonphysical.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at animal consciousness hardly answers the question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Either consciousness evolved twice, at least, across the long course of evolutionary history, or it evolved sometime before birds and mammals went on their separate evolutionary journeys. Both scenarios would give us reason to believe that nature can knit molecules into waking minds more easily than previously guessed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Science may not have satisfactory answers to the question of consciousness in my lifetime, such answers may not even be possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case the discussion raises an ethical conundrum. If animal suffering differs little from ours, history won’t judge us kindly. I spent years as a vegetarian, and reading this article got me thinking of going back to at least a low meat diet. If you’re starting out, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nomeatathlete.com/relax/&quot; title=&quot;No Meat Athlete&quot;&gt;the laid back guide to vegetarianism&lt;/a&gt; is about as sensible as you can get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;poverty-taxes-and-industrial-policy&quot;&gt;Poverty, taxes and industrial policy&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Louisiana should be among the richer places in the world. Instead, you see poverty akin to the developing world. The answer to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RWTic9btP38&quot; title=&quot;YouTube&quot;&gt;why Louisiana stays poor&lt;/a&gt; is surprising simple: companies pay almost no tax and receive huge subsidies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Almost all of the coverage about the Green New Deal has missed the mark. It’s a vast vision of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theatlantic.com/science/archive/2019/02/green-new-deal-economic-principles/582943/&quot; title=&quot;The Atlantic&quot;&gt;comprehensive industrial policy&lt;/a&gt; in the spirit of Alexander Hamilton. A sample:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;And arguments for the Green New Deal can even feel a little … Trumpy. When Gunn-Wright talks to people about the Green New Deal, “they get really excited about the thought of making stuff again,” she says. “That they’ll not just be a cashier, but that they’ll make wind turbines.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is about rebuilding the American industrial base and developing the technology for the next generation of industry. In short, getting rid of the rent-seeking billionaires and reclaiming the innovative spirit of capitalism.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><category term="books" /><summary type="html">The winter of 2018–2019 has been hectic with a new job and over a month on the road. Nonetheless, I’ve snuck in some reading time and mulled over plenty of ideas.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Socialism: What’s in a Word?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/blog/socialism-whats-in-a-word" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Socialism: What's in a Word?" /><published>2019-02-22T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-02-22T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/blog/socialism-whats-in-a-word</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/blog/socialism-whats-in-a-word">&lt;p&gt;Can I step into the current political discourse wearing my linguist hat on for a minute? Unless we agree on basic terminology, the entire conversation becomes meaningless.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The right-wing media have long called anyone on the left a &lt;em&gt;socialist&lt;/em&gt;. Let’s look at &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Socialism&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia: Socialism&quot;&gt;how Wikipedia defines socialism&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Socialism is a range of economic and social systems characterised by social ownership of the means of production and workers’ self-management, as well as the political theories and movements associated with them. Social ownership can be public, collective or cooperative ownership, or citizen ownership of equity. There are many varieties of socialism and there is no single definition encapsulating all of them, with social ownership being the common element shared by its various forms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not even Bernie Sanders or AOC are anywhere close to calling for private industries to be nationalized or taken over by worker communes. There are no mainstream socialists in American politics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I understand why people on the left-wing of the Democratic party are trying to reappropriate the term socialist. You’re not going to have a nuanced policy discussion with someone who’s frothing at the mouth and not arguing in good faith. It’s simpler to say, “Yeah, I’m socialist. So what?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, AOC and Sanders aren’t socialists, they’re &lt;em&gt;social democrats&lt;/em&gt;, which &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Social_democracy&quot; title=&quot;Wikipedia: Social Democracy&quot;&gt;Wikipedia defines as&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Social democracy is a political, social and economic ideology that supports economic and social interventions to promote social justice within the framework of a liberal democratic polity and capitalist economy. The protocols and norms used to accomplish this involve a commitment to representative and participatory democracy; measures for income redistribution and regulation of the economy in the general interest; and welfare state provisions. Social democracy thus aims to create the conditions for capitalism to lead to greater democratic, egalitarian and solidaristic outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So they’re just mundane capitalists that use market mechanisms such as regulation and taxes to promote positive outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The 2020 Democratic primary is going to be the only serious idealogical contest of the year: neo-liberals and social democrats are fighting for the next generation of party leadership. This is a real debate, in good faith, about differing visions of how to govern the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, calling everyone on the right a fascist is equally sloppy. To quote Orwell’s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://orwell.ru/library/articles/As_I_Please/english/efasc&quot; title=&quot;What is Fascism?&quot;&gt;What is Fascism?&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[A]lmost any English person would accept ‘bully’ as a synonym for ‘Fascist’. That is about as near to a definition as this much-abused word has come.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Focusing on the identity politics of Evangelical Protestants and White Nationalists is far more precise and useful. Discussing economic policies that favor capital over wealth, deficient spending and critically underfunding infrastructure is far more constructive than titling at the windmill of fascism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reclaiming meaningful words in our political discourse and avoiding the cheap buzzwords is another step in &lt;a href=&quot;/blog/how-democracies-die&quot;&gt;keeping our democracy alive and flourishing&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Derek Kedziora</name></author><category term="politics" /><summary type="html">Can I step into the current political discourse wearing my linguist hat on for a minute? Unless we agree on basic terminology, the entire conversation becomes meaningless.</summary></entry></feed>